Hello again. My name is Sophie Dove.
Previously, I gave you the lecture on nutrients. My plan today
is to introduce you to a few classic types of
experimental designs that are associated with identifying the influence
of a factor on a given response either
as part of a field study or associated with a manipulative experiment.
I will begin by introducing you to a few key terms and concepts.
Why do we conduct experiments?
Typically because we want to  precisely
and accurately answer some specific question or
questions. The answer usually involves
observing the impact of a treatment on a group
or collection of subjects. Prior to engaging in any experiment
it is important to identify known
or expected sources of variability as this will improve precision
and minimize bias. Professor Hoegh-Guldberg
spoke about precision in his field methods lecture
but it is clear that bias has to be eliminated
if the answers obtained to questions are to
overlap with the correct or true answers:
the truth. The following schematic
is intended to help you understand these terms
and their relationship to each other. Observations
are precise and accurate if they are closely clustered
and overlap the truth. Observations are
inaccurate but precise if they are closely clustered
but don&#39;t approximate the truth. They can be
accurate and imprecise when they overlap the truth
but are not closely clustered and they can be both
inaccurate and imprecise.
Clearly a key goal must be to eliminate bias
and improve precision. A step essential to this goal
is to ensure that background conditions are uniform across
all the treatments applied to all the experimental subjects.
Talking about &quot;treatments&quot; requires the introduction of a few more technical terms.
A factor is essentially a category
or type of treatment. Sometimes they are referred to as
&quot;controlled independent variables&quot; or &quot;categorical variables.&quot;
Here the application or presence of nutrients
is given as an example of a factor.
Factors have levels,
that is, the different amounts of the factor
that you are going to dose the experimental subjects with.
In this case there are three levels:
low, mid, high concentrations of nutrients.
Experimental designs can include
more than one factor. Therefore
the design of the experiment may be referred to
as a one factorial, two factorial
three factorial and so on experiment.
A factor is fixed when the levels under study
are the only levels of interest. A factor is random
when the levels under study are a random
sample from a larger population and the goal of the study
is to make a statement regarding the larger
population. Another way of understanding this
is that, if the level studied
divided by the levels of interest is equal to one
then the factor is fixed. If it is less than one
then the factor is random. Typically
the sex of an animal will be a fixed factor the levels studied
are male and female and for the most part
these are the only levels available, whilst the genotype of an animal
will be a random factor. You might select
to examine four genotypes from a population
that may include thousands of distinct genotypes.
If you recall Professor Hoegh-Guldberg
suggested that you add replicate experimental areas
to augment the level of replication in your experiment
and hence improve your ability to associate
responses with the different treatments, as opposed to mere inter-site
differences irrespective of the treatment.
For such an experimental design
the question is: are polluted sites different
from non-polluted control sites? The hypothesis would be:
polluted and controlled means for a specific response variable
are different. A description of the experimental design will be given as follows:
this is one factorial design where the factor
is habitat studied at two levels -
polluted and control - with three replicate
measurements determined for each level of the factor.
The factor is fixed because there are only two levels of interest for the
factor as we are not concerned with different amounts
of pollution in the present question just
presence and absence of pollution.
An alternative and commonly used approach that requires slightly more work
includes replicated transits within each
experimental area, in this case the question is slightly more complex
and asks: are the sites within a habitat
more similar to each other than the sites
between habitats? We can compare
amongst the experimental areas because we have more than a single transect for
each area. The hypothesis is then
that, the response variable - for example
abundance of sea cucumbers - will vary between habitats
and that differences will be greater than differences observed
on a smaller spatial scale.
It is a two factorial nested experimental design
the first factor is habitat with two levels,
polluted and controlled as before, we now
however, have a second factor - site -
with three separate levels or locations.
Habitat is fixed as before but site it random
because there are more than three locations we could have
selected from for each habitat level.
The nested approach is necessary becuase the same site can not be used
for both polluted
and control habitats. Again
this is a nested design because not all the boxes can be filled with data
when we tabulate the responses observed,
for example site one cannot be found
both in the control habitat and in the polluted habitat,
as a site can not be both polluted and clean
at the same time. When we select sites
amongst possible options it is important that we check that any differences
obtained
isolate our specific question from other
background conditions that may lead to obtaining significant differences that
actually have nothing to do with our specific question.
River plumes extend into significant portions of the Great Barrier Reef
following large rainfall.
A question that we might like to ask then is:
do the river plumes affect the distribution and abundance
of benthic coral reef organisms?
To assist with this aim, we might like to download satellite
image data that determines where the plumes extend to
within the Great Barrier Reef. Logically
the inshore because it is closer to the mouth of rivers,
is likely to be more affected than the offshore.
But if you select inshore reefs as &quot;plume affected&quot;
and offshore reefs as &quot;not affected&quot; it is possible
that non-plume effects drive any outcomes observed.
For example, upwelling and cooler water
may affect the offshore as opposed to the inshore reefs.
Likewise if you select your plume-affected sites from just the northern regions
and your plume-unaffected sites from the southern regions,
again these distinct latitudinal regions come with long-term differences
in temperature profiles. As much as possible
you need to select sites that eliminate these confounding background
features.
Here I hope to find satellite images
that would show the plume extending to the red sites
but not to the yellow sites, however this may not always be possible.
Furthermore your interest in river plumes may be tied
to the effects of either the nutrients or salinity
or sediment or pesticide concentrations
on the subject. However
it may not be possible to find sites in the field
that isolate these different drivers but otherwise have similar background
features. This is where manipulative experiments come into their own.
This brings us to the end of part one
of this lecture. In part two we will begin to take
a look at a design that is often used in manipulative
experiements to tease apart the roles
of different drivers or factors.
Thank you.